Hello friends, if you have had a root canal treatment done
and still you are experiencing
pain in your tooth, then your condition is
very similar to that of these patients. First of all, let us
know about Ravi's elder one. Ravi's
problem is that he completed the root canal
treatment and from the very next day he started having
severe pain in his tooth.
Although the pain gradually started reducing in two-three days,
but the
pain still remains in his tooth and he is confused as to what
he should do now. Tamste also
completed the root canal treatment and
from the very next day he started having severe pain in his tooth,
but his pain is not reducing but is
increasing and he is also confused as to what he should do
now. Anita's
problem is that after she completed the root canal
treatment,
she did not have any pain, but ever since
she got the cap fitted on her tooth,
she is not able to move anything from its place because she is having
pain in her tooth and she
also does not understand what to do next.
Aman's problem is  The thing is that he has
completed the root canal and also got
filling and camping done and it has been
a year since he got it done but
something always gets stuck in his teeth while eating
and then after that he starts having pain in his teeth
and he is also
not able to understand that he has
completed the treatment but
why is he facing this problem now. So if
you too have similar problems as this patient,
if you are facing any of these problems
then you should watch this video completely and
carefully because I am going to
answer many such questions in this video.
To understand the pain of root canal easily, I have divided this pain
into two parts, one is
immediate pain and the other is late pain,
which is the first day of root
canal completion, this means that it can occur between the day
you got the root canal completed and the
next 7-8 days
and late pain is the pain which lasts after 7-8 days.  It
starts after 7-8 days,
which means it can start after 7-8 days, it can
start after 15 days, after
a month, after 6 months, after a year,
after 2 years, anytime. There is also a
third part in the pain of root canal treatment
which is pain from neighboring teeth, about which
we
will discuss later, but first let us understand
why there is immediate pain and why there is late pain. The
first cause of immediate pain is
seen in the procedure. When root
canal treatment is done, first of all the
material is removed from the top and then the
root canal files are used from inside to clean the pulp
chamber, which is pulp chamber.
During this cleaning, the root canal
files go inside and touch the bone as well, due
to which the bone may get slightly injured
and there is some swelling in it.
Due to this also, you have to undergo root canal
treatment for a
few days,
so some chemicals are
also used.  And during root canal
filling, some materials are
used which, when they
touch the bone, can cause swelling in the bone
and due to this you may feel some
pain for a few days. So,
due to this pain of the root canal, you may feel
pain for 7-8 days even after the root canal is completed.
Another reason for immediate pain in the tooth is tooth
infection, which means that while doing the root canal,
some infection has gone inside
and this infection is causing the pain in the tooth.
Now the most important question arises
that how to identify whether this is the pain of the procedure
which will get cured very soon on its own
or it is the pain of infection
for which you will have to be treated again.
For this, I am going to tell you some very simple points,
you should look at it carefully. The
procedure pain will occur only when
you are touching the tooth with a knife or some
food etc. goes on the tooth and you are trying to remove
it from the tooth.
But normally, when you are sitting,
you will not feel this pain, meaning when the tooth is
not there or you are not touching the tooth,
then you will not feel this pain
and normally the pain gradually
subsides and goes away completely in seven-eight days. The
pain caused due to infection will remain with you the whole time,
whether you are chewing food or
sitting idle, this pain will remain with you the whole time
and this pain does not reduce,
rather this pain gradually increases
and even after 7-8 days, this pain will remain with
you. So these are some points by which
you can easily understand whether you are having
procedure pain or infection
pain. If your pain is procedure pain,
then you do not need to do anything in this.
Your doctor will prescribe you some painkillers
which you can take
and this pain gradually
subsides and goes away on its own.
If you are experiencing severe pain during this period, then
you can consult your doctor.  Painkillers
can be prescribed and
you can get relief from pain by taking these painkillers, but there is
no need to do any procedure in this. In case of
pain due to infection,
you will have to repeat the root canal,
which is called resection or root
canal treatment. If the root canal
cannot be repeated, then the tooth will have to be
removed. Now we know about late pain,
which usually starts after 7-8 days, or even
after eight days.
This means that it can start even after 7-8 days, it can
start even after 15 days, after
a month, after 6 months, after a year,
after 2 years, anytime. So
we are keeping it in the category of late pain.
See, first of all, it is very important for you to know
that root canal treatment is
not a single procedure. The success of root treatment
also depends on
how your root canal was done and
how your
root was cleaned during root canal treatment.  How is the feeling of the nerves done in canal treatment?
After feeling the nerves, how is the permanent
feeling done from above? And then
after all these procedures, how is the measurement of the cap
taken? How is the fitting of the cap applied?
What are its margins? So,
only by combining all these things your root
canal treatment becomes successful. If there is any mistake in
any of these steps, then
you may experience late pain i.e.
pain along with the protrusion.
Now I will explain to you how this happens
later. The
first point in late pain is relief. In Educate Your City, there is
a complete video of mine in its section which if
you watch, you will be able to know whether your
root canal treatment is done correctly or
not. If you are, then you can go and watch that video. So
I will not discuss much in its section,
but in short, I will tell you
that if the root canal treatment is
not done correctly and there is an infection in the nerves of the tooth, then
you may
also suffer from tooth pain later on.  The tooth may become loose
or a
small lump or a small hole
may form around the gums, which will form again and again and will move again and again.
If the root canal treatment is
not done properly, then this pain will gradually
become continuous. You will feel pain even when you are doing it in the tooth. You will
start feeling pain even while sitting and
this pain will gradually increase. It is
possible that there may be some enamel in the tooth which may
increase in a few years or it may
also happen that your tooth gradually starts
moving or a
small lump or a small hole may form in the gums present around the tooth.
Because it will form again and again and will get
displaced again and again. The only solution for this is that
you either get the root canal treatment done
again or if the root canal
treatment cannot be done again,
then you will have to get the tooth removed.
Another reason for root pain is the relief in adequate
feeling, that is, which you get after the root canal treatment is
completed.  Permanent
fillings are made if they are not done properly.
If these fillings are not done properly,
then gaps are created between the teeth and the
filling or between the filling and the
gums,
where food particles get
trapped and then they
create swelling and swelling in the gums and then you
gradually start feeling pain due to this. The
pain caused by these filled fillings is due to
food getting stuck and that
mild pain will remain in your teeth continuously. There are
very few chances in
which you will get severe pain. The
solution for this is that you should get the filling done in it
corrected so that you do
not have to suffer in future. The third reason for tooth pain is
inadequate cap margins, which means that the
cap that has been made for you is not made that well, so the
same thing happens in this also
when the cap is not made properly, so as
you can see in this photo, the cap is
not fitting properly on the tooth
and  Some space has been created in between them.
If the margins of the cap are kept like this, then
food will get stuck in them and there will be a hole in the
tooth and gum
problems will develop in the future. Therefore, it is
important that the margins of the cap are
made properly and their
fitting should be done properly as you can
see in the next photo.
In these photographs, you can see that the
fitting of the cap is good, the margins
etc. are looking fine, but if
observed closely, we will see that the
perfect fitting of the cap has
not come over the tooth and a little crack is
visible, meaning some space has been created
between the tooth and the cap. Although
this space is very less, but
how much space is needed for bacteria to live inside,
so leaving this much space and such a light perfection in fitting can
cause problems in the future. So, the fitting of the cap on the
tooth should be absolutely perfect so that there are
no problems in the future.  If it
comes then food will get stuck in it and the
teeth will start rotting inside and
gum problems will also start developing
and due to this, in the future, mild pain will start occurring
there. It is possible that this pain may
increase gradually. The
solution for this is to get the margins of the cap
fixed and if it does not get fixed
then the cap should be replaced i.e.
another cap should be put on. If the cap is
not correct then usually the pain that occurs is due to
food getting stuck and this pain is also
mild and the solution for this is
that you get the cap removed and another
cap of better quality should be put on its place. The
fourth reason for pain is the gap between the cap and the tooth.
You will come to know about this gap when you are doing something
and food gets stuck between the cap and the tooth.
If this is such a gap which is through and
through, from top to bottom, then the only
solution for this is that
you get the cap changed and with this, the cap of better quality
and butter fighting will be put on it.  Get the second
type of gap relief made. It
looks like this, which is a triangular shape relief.
In this, the relief of the tooth is in contact with the cap at the
top, but from the bottom,
where the gum and bone
damage has already occurred, the cap
cannot be made to touch the adjacent tooth.
This gap is formed due to infection or rust in your gums, etc. To
maintain it, you have to
brush this area properly.
Apart from this, there is no
other way to close this gap. But if
you do not brush properly or do not maintain it properly, then
food will get stuck in this gap and
then you may experience mild pain in the gums. The
solution for this is that you should
go to your doctor for scaling and cleaning
and then maintain this area by brushing properly. There can be
another reason for the gap, which
you can see in this photo, that on the sides of the
tooth on which the cap is placed.  There is a
cavity in the adjacent teeth and a gap is being
created at the place where the cavity is located. This
means there is no fault in the cap or the
gums. However,
if the adjacent teeth are hollow, this is why a gap is being created
and food gets stuck there. The
solution to this is very simple. If
you
fill the tooth with the cavity, the gap will automatically
close and food will stop getting stuck.
Now let's talk about the third aspect of the pain. That is, the
pain which is
not coming from the tooth with the root canal but is coming from the adjacent side. It
could be coming
from a tooth on the side or
from some other tooth, as you can
see in this X-ray. In this area,
five to six teeth are hollow and two
teeth have old root canal treatment,
which is not that perfect.
If you start the treatment on any one tooth
and finish it, then it is
possible that you may experience
pain again in that area.  In such cases,
doctors advise that you should treat
only one tooth for the treatment of the entire area,
but due to lack of time or financial constraints,
many times the patient completes the treatment of one tooth
and then leaves the rest of the teeth as they are, due to which
later on the adjacent teeth
also start paining and
then the patient feels as if he is having
pain in the one where root canal has been done,
whereas actually the pain is coming
from the adjacent teeth, so the
solution to this is that you should get the rest of the teeth
treated properly so that you do not have to
face problems in the future. I
hope you liked the video. Those who have
not subscribed to our channel are
requested to definitely subscribe to our channel.
Thank you very much for giving your time.